It started when I was a baby.
That's when I first saw it.
Shogi's been with me ever since.
I grew up in the northeast.
My village had snow and not much else.
There were more cows and roosters than people living there.
And of those people, most were senior citizens.
There weren't many other children my own age to play with.
Not even enough to play baseball or soccer.
That's where I grew up.
There wasn't much to do.
I could catch bugs by myself, or play video games, or read.
Then one day, as I sat alone by the heater,
a few old men from the neighborhood decided to teach me how to play shogi.
This piece here is the king.
That's the gold general.
Rook, bishop, and silver.
For games, manga, and novels,
the end always came too quickly.
Shogi was different.
There was no end to it.
I just kept going.
I was hooked.
I thought about nothing else after that.
No!
I can't believe that I lost again!
By second grade, I was beating all of the adults in the village.
And by the third grade,
I was taking the bus to study at a small shogi training hall in the city.
Even there, I continued to rise in the ranks.
Oh, great job!
You're amazing, kiddo!
My teacher from the training hall introduced me to Mr. Ouchi.
Under him, I joined the association in Tokyo.
For a middle schooler like me, Tokyo was a faraway place.
I had to take odd jobs around town to pay for transportation.
I'd pick apples and peaches in the summer
and help harvest rice in the fall.
And in the wintertime,
I worked hard taking care of the cattle.
Isn't Kai incredible?
He'll be famous one day.
Wait and see.
This young man might be the village's first magey.
The old men of the village were behind me 100%.
Thanks to my hard-won wages
and the encouragement of the old men
and the local shogi club members,
I continued going to the association
on that bumpy overnight bus.
That's when it began.
I've had issues with my stomach ever since.
It was just like everyone said.
The third den league was a den of wolves.
I was stuck there for years,
unable to advance.
I may have been hailed as a genius back home,
but in the city,
I was just one more brat with a shogi board.
In spite of my complete lack of progress,
the old men of the village never stopped believing in me.
Commuting on the bus overnight felt endless,
my seat squeaking and creaking all the while.
Eventually, it was difficult to know
whether all that noise was coming from the seat,
my stomach,
or if it was all in my head.
I would have awful nightmares
of riding on and on,
never getting anywhere.
Still,
I couldn't let everyone's faith in me
just go to waste.
I didn't want that.
Maybe that's the reason
why this pain
has me in its grips.
Excuse me.
Hey there, Kiriyama.
Oh, it's okay.
You don't have to get up.
I got you a few groceries.
I'll just put them in the fridge for you.
Thanks a lot.
It's nothing.
I'm on spring break now.
Have you had lunch yet?
No,
just tofu and a little something.
I can make you some noodles if you'd like.
They're pretty easy on the stomach
if you make them soft.
Oh,
in that case,
I might be able to have some.
Thanks.
My dad had stomach aches too,
so I know how that can be.
It'll just take a few minutes.
He did?
I didn't know that Mr. Kota had stomach aches.
Do you mind if I add an egg?
Not him.
Yeah, sure.
Please.
I see.
He meant his real father.
It looks good.
Not bad.
I think this will be fine.
Thanks.
That's great.
Good.
Well then,
if you don't mind,
I guess I should be heading home now.
Oh,
do you have to go?
Your fourth match is in five days,
so right now,
you need to focus on getting better
so you'll be ready for it.
It's important you don't overdo it.
Yeah,
I think I'll be all right.
These stomach pains are nothing new to me.
It's never really a problem during a match.
Uh,
you sure about that?
Yeah,
but with that being said,
however,
I found myself in a pinch.
I don't usually like to make any sealed moves,
but I had to this time.
During the natural flow of the game,
I came up with a really good move.
That's how I decided
on my sealed move.
But later that night...
Four-sixth bishop?
Not six-sixth silver!
Silver's same!
The six-five pawn
then takes that silver.
Rook at five-five
takes six-six lance,
but I overlooked that four-sixth bishop!
I'm a goner!
No!
You'll have me checkmated
before lunch!
By then,
it was too late.
Much too late.
So I spent the whole night
trying to think of a way
I could stay in the game.
And my stomach was on fire.
I tossed and turned
endlessly until morning.
Wait, what was it
that I was talking about again?
See?
This is exactly why
I'm telling you
that you need to rest.
Yeah, yeah.
All right.
Anyway, shall we?
I'll go with a static rook
and you go with a ranging rook, okay?
You're not listening to me, are you?
Are you sure about this?
Is it even useful
for you to be playing
against someone like me?
Am I the only one
who's benefiting from this?
After all,
I'm only C1
and you're A-class,
so there's a lot I can learn
by playing against someone like you.
But how
does it help you out
by playing against me?
Well, the thing is,
sometimes you sound like him.
It's how you phrase things.
Huh?
You remember?
You said it's unsettling.
Um,
how can I put this?
It just feels like it's
unsettling.
When Soya saw Silver to 3-7,
he said that too.
He was sitting in the waiting room
just talking.
That Silver to 3-7 move
was unsettling.
You know,
you two are kind of similar.
Not in any particular way.
But you both see the game
in a similar fashion,
and of course you're all-rounders
in your own right.
You're both very good
at offense and defense,
as well as your sense of timing
when you're making a decision.
So when you're sitting across from me,
playing as you do,
I feel like I can figure out
a tiny bit of Soya's thought process.
It's probably just temporary,
but it's better than
not practicing at all.
So tell me what Grand Master Soya
is really like in person.
Huh?
That's right.
Now that you mention it,
I guess when you've got
that many titles,
you don't really make your way
to Shogi Hall too often.
He probably just shows up
to sign certificates.
Let me see.
How do I put this?
He reminds me of a bird.
A bird?
Yeah.
Quiet and gentle,
like an egret or a crane.
It's sort of like
the story of the tortoise and the hare,
except he's much higher up
and seems to have
the presence of a bird.
Whenever I see Soya,
I pretty much feel like the tortoise
crawling along the ground.
And I don't mean that
in a bad way.
Not at all.
What continues to puzzle me
is that the hare's laziness
is caused by overconfidence.
But with Soya,
as you might expect
from someone labeled a genius,
he doesn't ever slack off.
No matter how high he climbs,
he never rests
and always maintains his confidence,
which is why I can never catch up to him,
no matter what I do.
I've been watching him all this time.
We're both the same age,
but he blew through the association
like a gust of wind.
I watched him go pro
and make quick work of the competition.
Just because there's distance between us
doesn't mean I should stop trying
to move forward.
Just because it's obvious
that I can't get ahead of him
is no excuse for not making the effort.
Mr. Shimada,
are you okay?
I think you need to see a doctor.
No, I'm fine, really.
I already saw one.
But Mr. Shimada...
I've got plenty of medicine, too.
I've been living with this pain
since my teens.
It's just part of my life now.
It does get old, though.
If only my stomach were a bit stronger.
Sorry, Kiriyama,
could you get me some water?
Oh, uh, yeah.
Sorry for asking you to come over here
when I'm not feeling so well.
I know.
Don't worry.
I really don't mind at all.
All right, then.
Would you mind sticking around?
A bit longer.
I won the right to challenge Soya.
So I can't let him win without a fight.
I've got to keep trying.
That's all that matters.
After all,
they still have the banner there.
It's in my local train station,
plain as day.
You know what's worse?
I'm the only one.
Nobody has ever made it this far.
I'm Yamagata's only highly ranked player.
That's why I have to do this.
No matter what,
I can't ignore that banner.
A lot of people are depending on me,
and I can't let them down.
There.
This train will be departing at 8.05.
I brought you a blanket.
And if you'd like to have some tea,
I'll put one here in the seat pocket for you.
Thanks for going to all this trouble.
The trip takes about two hours.
I'll wake you up when we get there.
So try to sleep.
Okay.
Thanks for everything, really.
No problem.
Later that night...
One more loss and the next is do or die.
All straight losses.
Can't let that happen.
He urged me to continue practicing with him,
even though he was still in great pain.
I'll be here for you.
It's no problem.
But I just can't let you travel alone.
Thanks a lot.
However,
as I watched Mr. Shimada sleep,
a strong sense of regret surged through me.
I never should have let it get this far.
I should have made him take a break.
We've now arrived in Kyoto.
Please remember to take all of your belongings.
Alright, so where do we find a taxi?
On the right,
facing Kyoto Tower.
Oh, right.
Take us to the second Kyoto Hotel, please.
Sure.
There he is!
Hey, Shimada!
Kiriyama!
Glad you could make it, too!
So sorry, Chairman.
We didn't mean to make you worry.
It's your stomach again, huh?
Man, you've always been so sickly.
Right?
Sorry.
Can't they just do a stomach transplant?
At this rate,
you'll never be able to win a title.
Sure, man!
You're just making things worse!
Well, never mind.
Go and get some rest until the reception.
Hey!
Can I get the bellboy?
I'll come by once you get some rest.
I put your phone and some water and tea next to your pillow.
Just give me a call if you need anything else.
You kind of sound like my mom.
Sorry!
My bad!
Am I being too pushy?
No, no, you're fine.
Don't worry.
Thanks for helping out.
So far, so good.
I wonder what I should do next.
Hmm.
I know.
I'll go pick up a book,
and maybe I'll get something to drink.
You know,
you surprise me, Kiriyama.
I always thought you were a pretty cold and distant kid,
but I guess I was wrong.
It's been a huge help,
you bringing Shimada here.
Well, I gotta get going.
I've gotta go and find Soya.
He still hasn't shown up yet.
Since he lives close by,
he always waits to leave home at the last minute.
He lives here?
Yeah, sure.
By the Silver Pavilion.
That place is incredible.
Don't all the tourists get annoying?
Not really.
It's actually pretty quiet there.
Is there anyone at his place you could call?
Nobody ever picks up.
You see,
he's living with his grandmother now,
and she's gotten a bit hard of hearing,
so...
I'm gonna go over there
and find out for myself.
So I'm back in Kyoto.
I haven't been here since I was in middle school.
Maybe I should pick up some souvenirs.
I wonder what Hina and the girls would like.
Hey, where's Kiriyama?
I don't know.
Who cares?
It's free time, right?
He can do whatever he wants.
Good point.
Guess I'll just head back.
There's nothing I really want to see here.
The pre-match reception for the fourth game of the Shishio Tournament
was held that night.
It was a grand gala.
Mr. Shimada was surrounded by the press.
He humbly responded with a smile,
answering their questions.
However,
he hadn't eaten anything since the night before,
and he was still in pain just a little while ago.
You can't do this.
If it keeps up till tomorrow,
you'll lose everything.
Yeah,
I'm painfully aware of the situation.
My most important job is giving everyone a good match.
It's also very important that I stand tall
before the people who were kind enough
to organize this event for us.
I understand that,
but still...
It hurt to watch as the cameras flashed at him.
Mr. Shimada...
I had the feeling that each flash
caused a burning sensation in Mr. Shimada's gut.
They're talking to each other.
Mr. Shimada?
I'm leaving,
stealthily.
So suddenly?
Are you okay?
Don't worry.
I did everything I had to do.
He wanted to help me out.
So I'll leave the rest to him.
Hey,
good job working the crowd.
Sorry for leaving early.
I need to get some rest.
Aw,
that's not a problem at all.
Really,
no one will even notice,
I'm sure.
Besides,
everyone's here to see...
Soya!
Understand?
So go ahead and get some rest!
Chairman!
I know, right?
As long as I say hello to everyone,
the rest of the night
pretty much becomes
a Soya photo session.
Yeah,
you've kind of always been
more of the Wallflower type.
You're practically invisible!
Okay, Chairman,
that's enough.
You can stop now, okay?
Really,
you don't need to say
another word, please?
He really does piss me off, though.
Always looking so young
and adorable
with a full head of hair.
Know what the craziest part is?
Your age!
You may be the same age as Soya,
but you look like
you're as old as Goto!
Oh, that's right, Kiriyama.
I meant to tell you
that Smith is going to help you out
with your room,
so go see if you can find him anywhere.
He's here as an assistant observer this year.
Uh, no, that's okay.
I'll go to an internet cafe.
Come on,
I can't let you do that.
Talk to him.
I'm sure Smith won't mind
sharing his room with you.
See you tomorrow.
Good night.
Have a good night!
Bye.
Even when he's in pain,
he still thinks of others.
Poor thing.
It's no wonder his stomach hurts.
What do you want?
I was just about to enjoy
some me time
in this fancy room.
Sorry, I'm fine.
I'll just go to an internet cafe.
I was just kidding.
Take it easy.
What a pain.
Knock it off!
Someone's calling.
Hold on a second.
Hey there,
what's going on?
It's okay.
How about you?
Oh, I was thinking
of calling it a night.
Yeah.
Uh-huh.
Really?
Acting all lonely
without me around, huh?
Uh-huh.
Oh?
Yeah?
A healthy appetite?
Ate every last bite?
Meow.
Hey, wait.
I heard something.
Was that my strawberry?
What?
How could you?
You're purring for someone else!
Huh?
A girlfriend?
And she's with someone else right now?
A love triangle?
Am I supposed to be hearing this?
Huh?
What?
She's on your lap!
No way!
How could she?
She hates when I hold her
and never sits on my lap!
Depressing.
Hey, um, Mr. Smith?
Kiriyama.
I need a drink.
Can I take the key?
Oh, my little kid.
See you later.
And then,
the night turned to dawn
as if nothing happened
and the time was finally here.
The fourth match
of the Shishio Tournament.
All right.
The time is nine o'clock.
Begin.
Defending champion,
if you will, please.
Let's have a good day.
I hope
Mr. Shimada was able
to get some sleep last night.
He looks exhausted.
Is he still having issues
with his stomach?
What should I have done?
Should I have refused to practice?
Forced him to relax?
It's too late
for me to regret
or take anything back
at this point.
The match had begun
and there was no way
of stopping it now.
So suddenly? It starts in 10 minutes!
It's gonna be fine, don't worry!
Sorry about that, Nikaido. I was gonna call you sooner, but I haven't had the chance.
I would have flown to him this time if I didn't have a match.
I wore a new Komodo just for the occasion! Let me be on TV!
It's Mr. Shimada's fourth match in the Shishio Tournament.
I'll have to make some more noodles.
Please watch the next March Comes In Like a Lion.
...